let set16 =
    [
        {
            question: `#1. Consider the following statements regarding in vitro fertilization. \n 1. In this technique, after fertilization, the zygote is allowed to develop for 7 days and then transferred to the mother’s uterus. \n 2. Baby born through this method is called test tube baby; because the development of the baby occurs in a test tube. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
            options:
                [

                    'A. 1 only',
                    'B. 2 only',
                    'C. Both 1 and 2',
                    'D. Neither 1 and nor 2',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: A`,
            exp: `Explanation: Fertilization occurring outside the body, artificially, is called in vitro fertilization. If the sperms are unable to reach the egg, due to blockage in the oviduct, the doctor collects fresh sperms and eggs; and fertilizes them in appropriate media for several hours, to bring about IVF or In vitro fertilization. If fertilization occurs, the zygote is allowed to develop for around a week, following which, it is transferred to the mother’s uterus. The test tube baby is born like any other baby and its complete development takes place in the uterus. A baby born through this,  technique is called a test tube baby. This is misleading because babies do not grow in a test tube.`
        },
        {
            question: `#2. The first step of reproduction is called fertilization. Consider the following statements regarding reproduction of organisms. \n 1. The fusion of sperms and ovum is called fertilization. \n 2. Fertilization in all oviparous animals occurs outside the female body. \n Which of the above given statement/statements is/are correct?`,
            options:
                [

                    'A. Only 1',
                    'B. Only 2',
                    'C. Both 1 and 2',
                    'D. Neither 1 nor 2',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: A`,
            exp: `Explanation: Sperm and ovum, both are examples of single celled bodies. The fusion of both is called fertilization, the result of which is the formation of zygote. The cells of zygote divide continuously, to form a ball of cells, after which, the cells differentiate and divide into tissues and organs. This is called an embryo. The embryo undergoes development after being implanted on the wall of the,  uterus. The stage of embryo development, wherein all the body parts are distinguishable, is called foetus. Animals which give birth to offsprings, are called viviparous; and the ones which develop through eggs are called oviparous. Statement 2 is not correct, because fertilisation in some oviparous animals occurs outside the body, and in some, inside the body. Fertilisation in chicken is an example of internal fertilization. In many animals (frogs, toad, fish, starfish, etc), fertilization occurs outside the female body. In these animals, fertilization occurs in water. As soon as the egg is released from the female body, males release the sperms. All the sperms swim in the water with the help of their tail. These sperms, on coming in contact with the membrane of the egg, result in fertilization. This type of fertilization, where male and female gametes fuse outside the female body is called external fertilization.`
        },
        {
            question: `#3. Consider the following pairs regarding reproduction and development of organisms. \n 1. Budding — Reproduction process in Amoeba. \n 2. Binary fission — Reproduction process in Hydra. \n 3. Metamorphosis — Transformation of the larva into an adult through drastic changes. \n Which of the pairs given above are correctly matched?`,
            options:
                [

                    'A.1 and 3 only,',
                    'B.2 and 3 only',
                    'C.3 only',
                    'D.1, 2 and 3',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: C`,
            exp: `Explanation: Like plants, animals too have two types of reproduction: 1. Sexual reproduction 2. Asexual reproduction The type of reproduction, wherein only one parent participates is called asexual reproduction. Budding and binary fission are methods of reproduction. Hydra reproduces through budding, and amoeba reproduces through binary fission. The transformation of the larva into adult through drastic changes is called metamorphosis.`
        },
        {
            question: `#4. Consider the following statements regarding cloning: \n 1. It is the process of artificially developing a tissue or any other living part of an animal. \n 2. A sheep, Dolly was the first successfully cloned animal.  \n 3. Dolly was a clone of the Finn Dorset Sheep. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
            options:
                [

                    'A. 1 only',
                    'B. 2 only',
                    'C. 3 only',
                    'D. 1, 2 and 3',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: D`,
            exp: `Explanation: Cloning is the production of an exact copy of a cell, any other living part, or a complete organism.Cloning of an animal was successfully performed for the first time by Ian Wilmut and his colleagues at the Roslin Institute in Edinburgh, Scotland. During the process of cloning Dolly, a cell was collected from the mammary gland of a female Finn Dorset sheep. Simultaneously, an egg was obtained from a Scottish blackface ewe. The nucleus was removed from the egg. Then, the nucleus of the mammary gland cell from the Finn Dorset sheep was inserted into the egg of the Scottish blackface ewe whose nucleus had been removed. The egg thus produced was implanted into the Scottish blackface ewe. Development of this egg followed normally and finally Dolly was born.`
        },
        {
            question: `#5. Consider the following statements regarding cell:  \n 1. It is the smallest living part of any living organism. \n 2. The first cell was discovered by Antonie van Leeuwenhoek. \n 3. The smallest cell is bacteria and the largest is ostrich egg. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
            options:
                [

                    'A. 1 and 2 only',
                    'B. 1 and 3 only',
                    'C. 3 only',
                    'D. 1, 2 and 3',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: B`,
            exp: `Explanation: The smallest living part of any organism is called cell. Hence, it is the structural unit of all organisms. Many cells together form the tissue, and tissue forms organs. The cells of cork were the first to be discovered in the year 1665; by Robert Hooke. Antonie van Leeuwenhoek was the first to discover bacteria. The smallest cell is the bacterial cell, and the largest is an ostrich egg; hence, statement 3 is also incorrect.`
        },
        {
            question: `#6. Consider the following statements: \n 1. Amoeba \n 2. Paramecium  \n 3. Hen's egg \n 4. White blood cells (WBCs) \n Which of the above are examples of unicellular bodies?`,
            options:
                [

                    'A. 1 and 2 only',
                    'B. 3 and 4 only',
                    'C. 1, 2 and 4 only',
                    'D. 1, 2, 3 and 4',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: D`,
            exp: `Explanation: An organism comprising of one cell is called unicellular. Amoeba, paramecium, hen’s egg and White Blood Cells are all examples of unicellular organisms.Organisms made up of more than one cell are called multicellular. In unicellular organisms, the single cell itself performs all the activities that multicellular organisms do, like respiration, growth, excretion, reproduction, etc; which are performed by groups of tissues in multicellular organisms.`
        },
        {
            question: `#7. The basic components of cell are cell membrane, cytoplasm and nucleus. Consider the following statements regarding these components of the cell: \n 1. Plasma membrane separates one cell from another and from the surrounding medium. \n 2. Cytoplasm is the jelly like substance found between the cell membrane and the nucleus. \n 3. Chromosomes are present in the nucleus. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
            options:
                [

                    'A. 1 and 2 only',
                    'B. 2 only',
                    'C. 3 only',
                    'D. 1, 2 and 3',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: D`,
            exp: `Explanation: Various components of the cell have a boundary, which is known as plasma membrane or cell membrane. This membrane separates one cell from another and also from the surrounding medium. It is porous and allows various substances t enter the cell. This membrane [provides structure to the plant and animal cells. Cytoplasm is a jelly like substance, which is found between the cell membrane and nucleus. The other components of the cell (mitochondria, golgi complex, ribosomes, etc) are found in the cytoplasm itself.,  Nuclei are circular in shape and present in the central region of the cytoplasm. The nuclear membrane separates the nucleus from the cytoplasm. This nuclear membrane is also porous ad regulates the incoming and outgoing of materials between the cytoplasm and the nucleus. This nuclear membrane is absent in the bacterial cells. Nucleolus and chromosomes are present within the nucleus. Chromosomes are present within the nucleus. Chromosomes carry genes and can be seen only when the cell divides. These help in inheritance or transfer of characters from the parents to the offsprings.`
        },
        {
            question: `#8. Consider the following statements regarding prokaryotic cells. \n 1. Nuclear membrane is absent in prokaryotic cells. \n 2. Virus and blue green algae are examples of the same. \n Which of the above given statement/ statements is/are correct?`,
            options:
                [

                    'A. Only 1',
                    'B. Only 2',
                    'C. Both 1 and 2',
                    'D. Neither 1 nor 2',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: A`,
            exp: `Explanation: The cells which do not have a well organised nucleus, are called prokaryotic cells. In contrast, cells with a well organised nucleus are called eukaryotic cells. Organisms with prokaryotic cells are called prokaryotes. Bacteria and blue green algae are the examples of the same. Virus are neither prokaryotic, nor eukaryotic. Organisms with eukaryotic cells are called eukaryotes. Onion and human cells are examples of the same.`
        },
        {
            question: `#9. Plant and animal cells are different from one another. Consider the following statements regarding these differences: \n 1. Animal cells, in contrast to the plant cells, have an additional boundary of cell wall. \n 2. Plastids are found only in plant cells. \n 3. There are many small vacuoles in animal cells, whereas plant cells have one, central vacuole. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
            options:
                [

                    'A. 1 only',
                    'B. 2 only',
                    'C. 2 and 3 only',
                    'D. 1, 2 and 3',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: C`,
            exp: `Explanation: Animal cells are devoid of cell wall. Cell wall is present in plant cells, apart from the cell membrane. It provides rigidity and shape to the plant cell. Bacterial cells also possess cell wall. Plastids are found only in plant cells. These are mostly variously coloured. Some of these have chlorophyll, which is a green pigment. Green plastids are called chloroplast, which provide green colour to the leaves. Animal cells have many small vacuoles and plant cells have one big, central vacuole. Hence, statement 3 is correct.`
        },
        {
            question: `#10. Which of the following cells act as messengers?`,
            options:
                [

                    'A. Spherical RBCs',
                    'B. Long branched nerve cells',
                    'C. Spindle shaped muscle cells',
                    'D. All of the above',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: B`,
            exp: `Explanation: There are many types of cells in the human body, which differ in shape and labour. The function of receiving messages and transmitting is performed by nerve cells. These cells are long and branched. Similarly, blood cells are circular and muscle cells are spindle shaped. In case of plant cells, amoeba is a cell which has an irregular shape. The irregular shape of amoeba results in the formation of pseudopodia, which provides it motion and helps in capturing food.`
        }
    ]